hi John how are you I'm good I'm good
how are you I'm good I'm good I've been
watching you talking to Jordan Hall I
feel like I've been watching you for a
long time already today I haven't had a
chance to respond Mary but thank you so
much for what you said the one comment
you made was extremely helpful
you mean about wondering why anyone
wouldn't have an objection yeah yeah so
are you getting that ah no but I was
talking to Paul today by the way we
spoke very highly of both of you
especially you Mary and I was saying
well I was concerned about the one
analogy I drew and you know Jordan had
sort of spoke back and say John is
trying to do this but it looks like
looks like in general people are
responding you know with charity but
I've never lost I'm grateful for you
saying what you said so I wanted to
thank you for that well you know all
right cool
so yeah one of the things I thought we
could talk about was to come back on the
issue of rationalization on the ground
in the ground of B and if we can see any
sort of person in there mm-hmm
and I've been thinking a lot about this
in the past few weeks especially using
original John by the way for the book
recommendations those were very useful
yeah and I very very interested in your
Regina's thought as you know JP I really
well you know I commented on it I really
liked the video you did sort of trying
to integrate era genus ideas was sort of
my ideas about the but you know the
bipolarity between emergence and
emanation I wanted to say right now that
that's very very close to how I was
interpreting in Aegina and why I was
attracted to him and so I wanted to
thank you for that I thought what you
did was very clear you're already
getting other people telling you that
that that video was a very very clear
video and I thought it was very well
and Mary thank you for the link you sent
me I haven't had a chance to look at it
yet about the era Gina talks but oh yeah
right I will do that well that professor
um thinks that era Gina should be up
there with Thomas Aquinas and Agustin
she's very thinking I would - I would -
and I mean era Gina's gonna figure in
the after Socrates video because I mean
what you see is dialectic of being taken
up right first of all it's written you
know the division of nature is written
as a dialogue right so it's very much
Socratic like that but then the
dialectic is it's sort of the the
culmination of the neo platonic vision
it's not only between people and within
thought but it sort all Tomica form -
the structure of being itself and so era
Jean is definitely going to be in the
acts of Socrates video series and so I
mean thank you both because it's very
helpful to me yeah and now I also want
to rather play mention you made a great
point I think when you talk to Jonathan
about Regina especially that one of
you're one of the reasons why you were
reticent to associate the original with
classical theism was that it was later
persecuted as a as a heretic yeah which
is really good evidence that he's
running afoul of classical so as I was
researching no even in general I also
tried to see a few reasons why it was
classified as a as they you hear it
again I mean because I don't Oh
ideally I would avoid try to I would
avoid being neurotic myself so I try to
steer away from this and there are a few
accusations which came up and as you
raised also with Jonathan it's not clear
exactly what your dream was persecuted
as he yes
comments all over the place um yeah yeah
one thing yeah one thing which showed up
was the accusation of the pantheism as I
said in one of the videos I think it's
something that I think it's kind of a
lazy accusation because you original
never tries to reduce God to anything so
yeah yeah I think that yeah I think
that's like when they
Socrates of atheism and corrupting the
youth yeah I think that way I think
that's sort of a that was sort of a
stand-in for some you know who this is
like paganism or something so I I
suspect that that's not that that's not
the thing I do I don't I do suspect that
the accusations had some sincerity in
them because he was thought of so highly
before he presented the division of
nature so I what I mean is it's like
again that the evidence is someone to
determine but it sounds like people were
sort of shocked when he produced it
because he had such a people had such a
high opinion of going in so I don't
think they were out to get him initially
that that so I I don't think that's
plausible either so there's some aspect
of his work that really really stepped
on people's toes and and his fall was
precipitous he was he was basically you
know the the court philosopher the court
theologian and then like many disappears
it's such an extreme fall the professor
that I was listening to today said she
made it sound like his he was actually
condemned many centuries or several
centuries later that it was he didn't
sound to me like she was saying it was
during his lifetime
after this scholastic oh yeah yeah yeah
yeah the official declaration of him his
heresy comes later but the idea is that
again my understanding and many people
with it's like this right is that
somehow goes back to something that
happened I mean like in his in his
lifetime that was my understanding
because like I said he's he disappears
and he disappears under a sort of a
cloud of suspicion you know my my
strategy to deal with this safety was to
try to then bridge from original to st.
Maximus the Confessor because Louisa say
figure because he's a saint and a priest
is insane so he's a saint in all
traditions so if I can make it there it
will be safer at least oh yeah that
would be fair to Jonathan too
Oh Joe because Maximus is pretty very
much his hero with you yeah yeah well we
I really like that conversation I mean
it got a little heady and so hopefully
we can make some some good analogies for
people who are watching so that we don't
get too too too too lost in sort of
concept space yeah I liked I liked the
discussion about relevance realization
and era Gina and what that might mean
and Jonathan had this very extended
notion of personhood you know which I
can't actually I couldn't quite make I
was getting pieces of it but I didn't
quite see how it work you know anyways
this was also get to one of the reasons
why original was seen as at least
suspiciously and ultimately condemned as
a heretic is there's a distinction in
which it sort of it sort of emerges in
especially the Christian East there is a
recent loss of her name David Russia was
written about this is it's the
distinction between essence and energies
especially in the eastern of their
extradition and apparently you can trace
it all the way back to st. Paul in in
his writings he is the first one to use
the terms of energies only when talking
about the actions or the manifestations
of iron level beings like like God or
demons and it's a distinction which you
can see also apparently in st. Maximus
and this allows them to explain ow so
you can have a vision of personhood with
sort of very deep manifestations and
ultimately one of the ways to see it
maybe is in the in the West there was a
as you as you point out John a natural
supernatural distinction which became
clearer and clearer and then fully
articulated with the same Thomas Aquinas
whereas in in the East instead of having
a very clean cut to world mythology it
was always more of a a continuous cosmos
where the distinction they see between
God's essence and his energies is not
like at one level you have a sense and
then at the other level you have
energies the energy sort of always
received it always depends on our on
where you stand on how you can look at
it so even anytime we comes up with
something simpler maybe like when my
essence and my energies like I'm a human
and I can as a human person as a human
hypostasis I can deploy some I can
manifest I can manifest the energies of
a human nature let's say I'm typing on
this keyboard I'm doing something very
human at this moment so only human
hypothesis I have the power to manifest
the the human nature there and in this
manifestation I can bring some some
lower beings into participation there
like my aunt for instance I can bring my
hands into typing on the keyboard and
the important point there is that when
my aunt participate in my energies in
mind my typing there they can
participate more or less like maybe I
have a disease in my hand and they don't
fully respond to our typing but if my
end my enter are fully healthy and they
fully participate in my typing they if
they be fully participate in my energies
then my end is also more fully a hand
it's healthier it does what it's
supposed to do and so on so yeah a
notion not only oh I am a human enzyme
an institution of the human nature I can
manifest this in doing certain things
and I can bring lower things in certain
positions in my energies and with this
distinction this allows st. Maximus to
do things especially I mean to do with
bodies which originate doesn't and some
things which seem very suspicious from a
Christian point of view
so for princess original doesn't think
that we add bodies before the fall and
also on the other end of the spectrum
it's not clear in original system why
the Incarnation was
was it important that they said the
logos became a body and also it doesn't
talk much about how we can participate
in this how we can participate in the
body of Christ whereas it's all over the
place if you read about few assists in
st. Maximus that define ization takes
place within the body of Christ or as
Mary you've been talking you know leaf
in your videos in a community of logos
it takes place with it so me really a
body
so this is those are all touch points
which you would you know doesn't
sometimes when you read the provision
you can see it even there where you
mentioned the Incarnation and the fact
that the word became flesh and so on but
it's not clear why it matters really it
doesn't give the sort of precise
arguments which Maximus is able to give
and I think it will come down to this
link between our lessons when it's
instituted into a person between
apotheosis can then manifest itself at
those different levels what is the
difference between what you're calling
energies and what we would call works
that's a good question I would do in
bank works especially with what sort of
bit of examples we have well like just
what you said about like typing on the
computer it's like it's you're doing
you're doing work right and I'm isn't
there isn't there etymologically a
connection between the word energy and
the word work it's odd atom illogical as
definitional energies the capacity to do
worked with in physics okay okay that's
what I thought you know with some
connection so would so I guess my my
question is then what's the difference
between what you're describing when you
talk about like typing on a computer or
doing something that you know it's like
your essence becomes manifested through
a work well I don't see the difference
between and we're done today I wonder
why are we using the word if energy is
the capacity to do work but you're
talking about the doing then why
using the word continuing good point
one the important thing is that
especially in the East they will
identify in a I guess in an illogical
way in d the hypostasis
with the the energies so in the case of
God for instance if you participate in
God's energies you do participate in God
so actually don't participate in God's
essence is that the idea
nope not in existence we we humans never
reach God's essence we can't participate
to diverse degrees in his energies so
even the mere fact that we exist is is
signifies that we're being held in
existence by the common being so we
participate in the energies to this
extent but we can participate more fully
they see like when I was talking about
my hand know my end if it's if it's sick
in responding properly it's still for
them it can still participate in what
I'm doing but to a lesser degree then
weighted food when it fully obeys when
it fully becomes part of part of me and
but I'm interested in the participation
the other way JP you know maybe Mary is
- I'm interested not so much how your
hand can participate in things I'm
interested in is the relationship is a
relationship of participation between
the dynamics because that's what you
would say in your aerosol between the
dynamics of your hand and your essence
like your hand is part of your identity
such that if I if I cut your hand you
say oh you cut me right you don't see
right you know and I'd be guilty of
hurting you as a person if I damaged
your hand is that what's being invoked
here that you know that I mean it I mean
if they talk about the hand of God in
the Bible so what might we could even
use that as a metaphor perhaps I mean is
you know I'm trying to I'm trying to see
what this does in terms of our
participation in God that's what I'm
trying to get it so the idea is we could
we can interact with God's hand and
God's hand has a participatory
identity with him but God's hand is not
his essence is it something like that
I'm trying to understand what's going on
yes yes
so we yes I'm not sure I see you the
point you just read about how you wanted
to see the other way around in the way
oh my and you were telling me how the
Hitman you're here could participate in
the world but I was interested in how
your hand participates in your essence
okay trying to get out I'm trying to get
him I'm trying to get at the relation
with him God between his energy and his
essence what's that what's the nature of
that relay relations because there's
there's must be some metaphysical
difference because I can participate in
God's energy according to you you know
but I can't participate in God's essence
so there the relation can't be one of
identity between God's energy and his
essence but it can't be one of this
identity or then I can't enter into a
relationship with God that's what that's
what I'm trying yeah that's a very deep
question and I suspect that this will
have something deep to do as well with
our original reunites the four divisions
of nature in because ultimately all the
divisions do well together there's a
sense in which they see the created
uncreated mm-hmm they created on
treating is part of God itself in being
in God it cannot exist outside of it or
it will just see existing so there has
to be a relationship that's hard to
articulate and I think this is what
they're pointing at with the essence
energy distinction but I mean it's
something like then I mean it's it's
something like you know and Jonathan was
talking about this you know the
Neoplatonic idea that the hypostasis
right it's it's not it's not it's not
essentially identical to that with it
that's why it's a relationship of
participation right the intellect the
the the the realm of the forms the inner
pair the eternal interpenetrating system
of the forms in the platonic sense
participates the one it's actually a
transitive verb right it participates
the one it proceeds and returns
but it is not identical to the one and
it sounds like your truck you're saying
that you see maximus doing the same kind
of thing yeah but I do think that also
as Jonathan said that in Christianity is
like the most important thing is that
the infinite is equal with the
manifestation of the infinite that you
you really do want to identify yes God
is energy okay okay so okay so okay now
I see so did so you're suggesting that
the the participation of God's essence
into his energies it does not have the
dominion did the diminishment in being
that the Neoplatonic process of a nation
as it is that is oh I see yes that that
I would say that's really I would say
that that's really key yeah yeah work so
and this is where I would think that we
make the great distinction between the
created and the uncreated that God the
uncreated and all of the creation right
that okay let's see how I can put this
into words so the the the things that
are contingent the things that are
created can participate to a greater or
lesser extent in God's energies by
cooperation okay and this would
especially be true of the intelligent
creation which can choose to cooperate
right but as but they're it's not as
though it's not as though God is sending
forth beings that are less and less and
less him down down hmm I'm kind of
losing a the way to express it
okay maybe JP kind of understands what
saying we're not we're not like
everything that in a set there's a sense
in which everything that is created from
the highest angel to the you know lowest
you know slug to every you know Adam is
is in a way um he equal in being
creation
yes contrasted to God who is uncreated
okay so let me give you an example this
is something I thought of years ago but
it's like it's just an illustration so
many years ago there I don't know if was
National Geographic Scientific American
or what magazine it was but they would
have a page in there and what they would
be doing is showing you something a
great magnification yeah and then you
would try to guess what the thing was
and you were you could never guess
really because it would be so different
from the thing that you saw if you
looked at the thing one time they had an
image that it looked like the surface of
the Moon with all these craters and
everything it looked just that you know
like the world like there were um cliffs
that you could fall over and all of that
and then you know you tried to guess
what it was well it turned out that it
was the surface of an egg hmm okay would
you wait which seems so smooth to you
when you hold it in your hand right even
though it might have slight texture it
doesn't look anything like it it's got
two craters and cliffs on it and I
remember thinking when I saw that I
remember thinking down here in the realm
of creation or down here on earth we see
so many differences you know we like
even between human beings and we're
always looking at you know who's at the
top of the hierarchy and who's in the
middle of news at the bottom
all these differences but maybe I
remember having this thought maybe from
God's perspective we're all equal
because I turn off my email
so anyway does that does that make sense
as an illustration of what I'm trying to
say that the difference there's really
this absolute difference between the the
uncreated between God the ground of
being and all of creation that there's a
way in which all of creation is actually
just that has the same status it's not a
it's not a it's not a diminishment even
though think I think I think there's
definitely a diminishment just I think
to do with the fall that's fall for just
a minute just to talk about it in terms
of the creation for a minute because we
can always come back and talk about the
fall you know sorry Barry I wanna make
sure you done yeah
so I'm trying to get yes I think I'm
getting a glimmer but I'm not it's not
clear because I'm trying to and I mean
this was a point that Jonathan was also
he was trying to you know emphasize that
there right there's kind of that
Christianity sees goodness throughout
whereas Neoplatonism sees a diminishment
as things emanate okay
and so is that now one of the things
that of course for me a deep innovator
so in new platonism you have the
procession you have you moved from
singularity not not which is not the
same thing as a single it's kind of like
the singularity of the Big Bang right
it's not it's not it's that kind right
it it's condemned debate it's all
intelligibility back to its ultimate
unity etc and then it proceeds out but
the
everything is also simultaneously
returning which you know right but the
the the big difference I think in era
Gina for me and why I'm so interested in
and I'll give me a second guys and I'll
try and connect those two points
together so I don't mean to trust fasten
your patience right is right for
platonist for example if there is the
didn't there's the diminishment all the
way down right and there's a sense of
which the emergence isn't really the
return isn't emergency you know in the
sense I would talk about it it doesn't
contribute it's just it's a return think
of the language right um so for example
if I go down and Platonists like yet at
the bottom which is pure right pure lack
of form pure matter and for Platonists
that's pure evil
right but what I see in era Gina is no
no that's for him right that's the flow
the way you're explaining it to it I
think you agree with it that's the
inexhaustible right and that's from
which every an emergence is just as if
you'll allow me this word I don't mean
to trespass on your space but the
emergence upward is just as sacred as
the emanation down right because the
emergence upward expresses the
inexhaustible in a sense and then the
emanation down expresses the ultimate
unity and integrity of intelligibility
and both of those are worthy of
sacredness is that yes yes yeah and
that's why I wanted to mention the fall
just because you coming down and going
back there's another language we could
use we could use origin and Tilos right
well Tilos is really the origin right so
we could talk about beginning and end
alpha and omega yeah yeah so I'm
interested yeah I mean well I think they
should I think the vertical ontological
and the horizontal historical actually
should be sort of triangulated but
because in era Gina they're supposed to
be triangulated into something that
transcends both of them in him I
understand it
so I think using both is is good but I
think they they pre go different aspects
I don't know this is important at that
point right now I guess what about what
I'm interested in is what Mary said
first I also want to hold off before we
get to the fall if that's okay
so I'm trying to understand Mary because
I can see I was trying to capture the
smoothness of the egg is one way in
which it's sacred because the smoothness
points towards that that the oneness of
the intelligibility but the differences
of the a is all those differences
actually generate all of the capacity
for for things to emerge for new things
to happen and and so and that's also
worthy of being thought of as sacred
justice as much as as as the smoothness
of the egg the dappled it's like you're
out manly Hoffman's right the dappled
nurse of things it's just as much as a
sacredness as the smoothness if I could
usually metaphor is that doing justice
to what you were saying yes all creation
is good yes but but but but the I'm
trying to get that there's two different
languages go ahead JP I'm talking too
much I definitely agree with the to the
fact that there is emanation from God
from the ground of intelligibility and
emergence from the common being and to
meet the inexhaustible and the ground
what you don't need they completely
interpenetrate yeah yeah yeah yeah every
place where do you meet then things
exist in creation exists that's right
and that's the dialectic that's the
dialectic in creation yeah yes and this
is what I I this is where participation
can come in as well because we can
frustrate this or such if we do not
participate in being properly we can
avoid the emergence from reaching what
it should yes this is why I wanted to
mention the fall and here was this also
ultimately in especially
that's I think this could be one of the
reasons why my and example was was a bit
messy at the beginning because no I'm
not perfectly identified with my
manifestations and similarly right now
you can say that the the the emergence
and the emanation are not in the proper
relationship because we're after the
fall but the idea is that especially the
human being and especially in the
original as the role of working in this
relationship between Negro being in the
ground of its logic intelligibility we
have the before the fall and then after
its services we have the role of
mediating between the two so there's re
fracture in being yeah I get that and I
think I mean and and the point of the
dialectic in the division of nature is
to exemplify how we can come into
control how we can come into greater
conformity not in what we say but in
what we in how we think and interact
with each other so it's more about our
being and that is how we can come into a
better alignment with sort of you know
the flow of the dialectic of being I I
think I think that's deeply right so
it's what I wanted to say I mean this is
what was also going on with with
Jonathan is for me so be charitable to
me guys I'm trying okay so in in deep
learning which is you know some of our
best artificial intelligence and it
looks like how the brain and this is and
I make use of it and relevance
realization and that's where Jonathan I
made it might have had a connecting
point what you see is you see it you see
the system cycling you see the system
cycling so what it does is it does
compression and it tries to get what is
invariant and in that sense eternally
sort of one and then it flows out to all
the variations right and then they are
gathered back up again and that's of
course you know the model of relevance
realization the model of evolution and
for me right I was thinking oh that's
kind of interesting because that might
be a potential way of seeing something
deeply analogous but we
which is what you and I've been talking
about JP and you and all three of us
last time Mary is that there's something
analogous you know it's a it's an invest
in I are an Augustinian idea you know
that sort of the not content of our
ideas but the very structural functional
flow of our mind is something that
reveals the structure the deeper
structure of reality so okay you can see
the flow of relevance realization as
deeply conforming to era Gina's
dialectic of being that's what I was
that's what I was that's where I saw as
a potential connection point between
Jonathan and I is that is that fair to
say that yeah did you say Mary I want to
hear from you well I want to say that
you know I like all of this stuff I've
loved everything you've done with the
relevance realization okay so if you you
talk about so there's something deeply
analogous between our mind and then
structures of reality sure deep
structures of reality and and I would
say and also the structures of reality
all the way up like all the way up and
all the way down right though so like we
may find that there like even like the
formation of crystals or something like
that is I think the the auto pieces and
relevance realization has a deep
continuity with some organization of the
fire etc yes I know what so don't know
more like to JP's points about Willis
this goes down but also why wouldn't it
continue to go up and so then I have to
come back to the question that's kind of
like the point of the point of attention
between us which has to do with why
wouldn't that be mind on there and a
person you know because it seems to me
that we that we value mind sure we value
mind over matter
you know we that we value mind over
matter because it's the mind that
to use pomander clays wording right
colonizes the matter right so we and we
value mind over matter give me an
example in an example like if someone if
someone um injures me let's say someone
hits me and harms me in some way okay so
there's the physical reality of that
thing happening but my my sense of that
incident is that vary greatly between
whether that person accidentally hurt me
or had the intention to hurt me right so
we're not the mind the mind the state of
the mind if we've we value it over the
over just the map the material reality
so I mean in some sense as I understand
you but so what I'm trying to get at is
if we value mind if we value mind over
matter okay and if if we can't go up
above the human in value then then isn't
it the case that we have to look and go
well we're at the top you know the human
the humans are at the top because we're
the ones with the minds and we're the
only ones with minds and therefore we're
at the top so okay now I see what you
mean
okay so you want you the idea is more
overvaluation i me because there's other
ways this well i because there's other
circumstances where we give priority to
the physical over our the mentor like if
i if I'm causing you hunger that's
considered a greater crime that I might
just sort of insulting you and giving
you a painful mental state right so but
I did I want to put that aside because I
was misunderstood
I think the way I'm understanding you is
saying the the thing that we think is
most inherently valuable in all of
creation or people is that is that a
fair way of putting it well or let's say
persons yeah wait person okay and so
and so if when you talk about things
coming down like you it sounds like it's
something above us but how can it be
above us if it's not first not a person
in what way well I mean it's above us in
terms up well III I want to go slowly
here because there's many ways in which
that could be answered so I'll say one
and then maybe I mean it's it's above us
in that it it everything else is
asymmetrically dependent on it all right
so that means that if realness is
actually what we is another thing with
that we intrinsically value which I
think we do then something being more
real in that sense in that more of
reality is dependent on it would make it
more valuable than me even though it
does it's not it's not necessarily a
person that's what that's what I wanted
to say I wanted to say but we value I
think there's things we do find
intrinsically valuable other than
persons I think we find things being
real read the realness of things is
inherently valuable to us to I mean
that's that I think that's a great
platonic insight that no matter what we
no matter what fulfills our desires we
have the meta desire that it's real what
fulfills our desires realness is we
value realness for its own sake right on
this on this one or this being whatever
I'm not sure what language you're using
for it when you say dependent dependent
for a dependent for continued existence
dependent for the origin of existence
oh no yeah so I would I mean it's a
ground
it says JP said it's and let's say in in
Regina not just pure neoplatonism its it
is simultaneously the ground of being
and the ground oven of the
intelligibility appeared yeah okay
so it's it's it's the story
everything is depended
everything I say is gonna be over
speaking of it everything is dependent
for it in terms of it being a being
every being is dependent on it insofar
as it's a being and every way in which a
being is intelligible is also dependent
on it so how does how does it so then it
must know intelligibility well - for
example argues that that's a mistake
because the ground of intelligibility
can't be an act of knowing because the
act of knowing depends on the the
depends on the principle of
intelligibility for example knowing is
about in a relationship between a
subject and an object but the ground of
intelligibility is what ultimately
unites and makes possible the
relationship between subjects and
objects so it can't itself be divided
between subject and object so it can't
therefore be an act of knowing the
ground of intelligibility can't be an
act of knowing any more than the grounds
of being can be a particular being yeah
I think that's what in the east they put
it in the energies rather than the
essence itself and I think we can forget
- Jonathan said this even about just
humans it's not they say the fact that
no I am the instantiation of a human
nature and you're the instantiation of a
human nature that makes us conscious
individually is the fact that we
interact between two different human
hypotheses it's in demand our
manifestations that there is
consciousness that there is what we
typically talk about special personhood
and I think it will be the same thing in
the case of if we talk about the drama
being it's in the East they can remain
apathetic about what happens in the
ground being itself in in its essence
and there's a sensibly I mean I want to
keep talking to you guys because it's
great but I don't want to dismiss that
and I think there's a sense in which we
should ultimately all recognize that
there's an aspect of this before which
we should have a kind of referential
silence I don't want to dismiss that
aside you know let's keep talking of
course because we
we're doing something useful here but I
just wanted to put that in because I
think that is important to say yeah yeah
I think I think that's that's very wise
thing to do and that's what if they all
be all that they will really need for
classical theism at least in the east is
that we can see we can use the modern
term of professionalization in the
manifestations of the ground of being
and we can remain an apathetic about
what happens within yourself about with
let's say the relationship between the
ground of intelligibility in the ground
of being what happens between the
relationship in themselves I don't know
we won't reach this point anyways so
then it becomes more of a question of
how is it that the ground of being
manifests itself does it do it in a way
that looks like reverse transition in a
way that we would associate with
personhood or would it rather be
something like emptiness like the
Buddhist conferences yeah so I'd be
happy with that and so the
way in which I could talk about that
that might upset you guys as I would say
well of course our non-theist would say
that often we will enter into personal
relationships and perhaps entering into
a personal relationship it you know it
is is a valuable way of disclosing
certain aspects of the one or the ground
of being in the ground of
intelligibility I'm going to use the
word one but I'm going to be using it in
era genus sense not just in China
systems because we need we need a term
of reference or for what it is I'm
talking about and so the the more
important issue then might be what you
want to say I I think there's a move you
can make and I maybe I'll make it on
your behalf and you'll stay aha but John
we we sort of we were talking earlier
about how the manifestations have a kind
of they participate the one in some way
so there's something if the personal
relationship participates the one then
there's something being disclosed about
what the one is even though it's not
part of the essence of the one it's that
kind of move you're trying to make is
that yes yes okay the only remaining
move that we may or may not make and
it's not sure it's in like a medieval
dispute in the east in like the 40s but
there the move is that you know the same
sort of manifestations which let's say
we see between us and the one could well
old within the one between let's say the
gonna being and the run of intelligible
this may be this is at or that could be
open as well that it could be difficult
in unity between the manifestations we
observe between humans and the between
humans and the one and also within the
one himself but we can I think most as a
quotes of Christians would be happy to
remain apathetic about what this board
okay so let me give you an example of
what I'm talking about so I I sort of
spoke on your behalf and I you said you
thought it was charitable um so let me
let let's take like Vedanta as at least
something that's officially supposed to
be a non-theistic because Brahman is is
is impersonal
but Vedanta says that the individual
gods right are the personal
manifestation so that we can enter into
personal relationships but Brahman is
itself right impersonal that's what I
mean about you can use all the language
we're agreeing on here and then still
ultimate ultimately say because that's
what the dancer does but ultimately
non-theism that's that that's that that
was the point I'm trying to make well I
think I think this accords well and I
don't know if you got to share my last
video or Paul Bantu plays video where he
talked about the meta divine realm
you know that many polytheistic systems
also posited a meta divine realm and the
meta divine realm could be personal or
could be impersonal or it could be a a
fight or a battle or contest so you know
we know that when we are talking like if
we go back to classical theism even when
we're talking about when we're talking
say about the Trinity when we're talking
about God you know
God as God and God the three persons in
God that we we know we're talking
analogously analogously to per to person
and yet there's a relationship so so
we're not so the idea that you know that
God transcends the category of person is
already part of it's already part of
Christianity so um so I don't have I
don't have an and don't have such a
problem with that um you know I think
there's there's tremendous like I say
there's a lot of there
a lot of utility definitely in person in
a personal God in many many ways
I mean psychologically for humans there
certainly is plus if that if there is a
real revelation you know which we
believe there is that there is a
revelation that God gave us to enter
into this personal relationship with him
so so we're not you know we can grab
many things but at the end of the day
we're we're sticking with a God who is
personal that's not to slight or to say
that that's not to make that's not to
make light of or not respect the
experiences and the traditions of those
who say this God is not personal because
even for those who have a non-person or
got the ground of being more
intelligibility it's not personal
because usually in almost all cases as
far as I know there are personal
entities that that come between the
human person and background of being
such that like as you said that a
relationship can can form and so I don't
I guess I you know we we talked before
about the ambiguity you know they taking
that as as seriously as as possible or
as you know as factually as possible you
know when we talk about how things are
how the the structures of reality go all
the way down and through I think this
applies even to our like to how we
relate to persons in the sense that if
when we're in doubt as to whether
there's a person there when we have an
ambiguous situation in life we go for
the person for example it uses an
example in one of my videos
if someone is going to knock down a
building and they're in doubt as to
whether there's a person there they
don't knock the building though you know
or try think I'd use it Oh a hunter a
hunter out in the woods if he sees a
movement behind a tree and he's not sure
if it's a deer or a person he doesn't
just shoot because it doesn't matter if
it's a person so like we we opt for what
do we have in a bigger situation in this
in life we opt for person okay I think
that's very good Mary and so I want to
respond to that in depth and then maybe
it will actually be a response that
closes some distance um first of all I
want to bring out that I there was two
parts to my argument there was the
ambiguity right and then there's also
that there is no logical decidability
for similarity there's no there's no
algorithm that can say this is this is
objectively more act is objectively more
similar than why because well if you
remember the argument any any two
objects are actually indefinitely
similar to each other or indefinitely
dissimilar to each other logically so
there's no algorithmic there's no
logical there's no way you give a
deductive evidence or proof or decisions
or teaser for similarity so I just want
to point out that though that's both of
those so that means that actually puts a
lot of weight on the pragmatic aspect of
your argument do you see what I'm trying
to say is dude you can't sort of say oh
here's the rule and if you follow it
that will show that this is the correct
analogy which is not what you're doing I
just want to make it really clear the
way it will read of where we're playing
right okay so and then the the the the
issue but the pragmatism is again what
that it's so pragmatism is ultimately
how things are relevant to us and you
know I'm sort of on record as saying I
don't think there's anything that's
ultimately always always has priority
and relevance and so I do think we do
make those kinds of decisions again when
we have moral concern but when we have
epistemic concerns we sometimes go the
opposite way we say for example we got
we made tremendous
progress and disease when we stopped
personalizing diseases and realizes
realize that they were created by these
impersonal forces bacteria etc things
like that when we stop thinking of them
as demonic possession etc we made we
made tremendous progress and we
alleviated a lot of suffering and so you
can say well in that situation you know
it was actually the better going
impersonal actually had great moral
benefit too and so the right thing to do
there was to actually you what we did
which was to go impersonal and thereby
we were able to alleviate so much more
suffering than when we treated the
unknown thing as if it was a person so
again you see what if I'm not I'm not
trying to one-up you Mary I'm just
trying to say yeah I'm trying to say you
know III I think there's context in
which you're right there's context in
which we say there might be you know
there might be a person there and that's
what I should do but there's other
contexts in which it turns out notes
sort of taking the risk that it's an in
first so no thing has actually had huge
moral benefit for us that's why I try to
give that example in the arena of
gratitude and Thanksgiving ok this is
another one of you good arguments I hope
you take that I'm responding to you with
some good arguments as indication that I
think you're giving good arguments and I
hope that's understood I want everybody
who's hearing me to hear that so I like
I thought I thought a lot about that
because and you mentioned I think very
correctly that you know the expression
of gratitude is part of what is part of
my daily practice for example and and I
was I was trying to think about so the
idea is first of all I want to make sure
I understand you so this is not a
challenge at criticism this is an open
question
it's the is the idea that what part of
the phenomenology that needs personhood
is that people experience deep gratitude
and it's not to another human person and
it's not to a collective
a bunch of you but there's there's a
sense of gratitude it's real and there
needs to be like what we're do I want to
use someone nice ah yeah there needs to
be a someone to whom the gratitude is
directed and so what I think my question
is what's the nature of there needs to
be as someone is it the idea that if
there isn't someone there my gratitude
will sort of dissipate and be frustrated
I'm trying to get the phenomenology that
you're pointing to well
what I'm I come back to the if there's a
person versus if there's not a person so
for example if which would be which
would be the better option to to say
thank you to a person who is not there
or to fail to thank a person who is
there well I I get your point we would
generally say it would be better to you
fail when there's no person there then
fail when there is a person there I get
that and I want to acknowledge that but
here
Spinoza famously said in the ethics that
the wise man desires nothing less than
to have God love him in return because
if he is desire and forgot to love him
in return that he's not actually loving
God for being God he's not actually
loving God has an exposed a is a pure
expression of the goodness of being and
so aha what are you loving her are you
are you not loving a who no for spinosus
God is much more I think you could make
a really strong case that but because
it's God or nature right for but knows
it means the things that we have
separated in terms of God and creator
and God in nature are actually
ultimately just one thing God or nature
and that is what he means by God and so
he's not loving a who he's he thinks
he's arguing that
if we actually care about the truth as
truth then we should love the ground of
being without desiring that it love us
in return because only the love for it
without wanting the love in return is
actually the love of truth because if
it's anything else I'm not loving it
because it's true I'm loving it because
of what it's doing for me that was sort
of you know in Christianity we do say we
do say that we love God for who he is
but it's that it's a it's a much more
less developed form of spirituality to
be loving God because what he does for
me I could be but that but that God is
deserving of of love for who he is
so that okay so let's at least say
there's something close between what
your identity and what Spinoza is saying
well and then it's
as what I am loving is good like the
truth is good then can I not love it and
be grateful for it without it being a
person well I mean there's a difference
between grateful for something and
grateful to someone for the thing yeah
but why do we okay but I acknowledge
there's the difference but our question
is which one of those is the one that is
happening in for example in my
phenomenology but I I expect I
experience deep gratitude for the
goodness of the ground of the England
for the ways we've been talking about
today and for the ground of
intelligibility and I don't desire for
the Reapers because I'm a deep devotee
of Spinoza I don't desire that it love
me in return I thought for me that would
be a diminishment of both what my love
is directed to you and of my love well I
I understand that I mean I I understand
what you're coming from okay so where do
these things you're grateful for come
from them I mean we get into questions
about you know basically the
cosmological arguments about that so the
part of the reason for the ground of
being is also the origin of being in
Christian thought so and one of the
reasons we say that there has to be and
this is apart from any other
distinctions about God like Trinity or
anything like that is that their hat
there there was a willful decision to
bring things other than God into being
exact
that makes sense what I'm saying that if
God that there was there was just God
and now there's other things other than
God that have a real existence that are
really that really having existence not
that they're not held in existence by
God but that they're given by God a
certain kind of freedom to be to be
actual um
to make things happen in the universe to
be causes in their own right causes but
the first cause is a is a decision so
your seems to be in your ontology you're
lacking an explanation for this was it
Leibnitz who said why there is something
instead of nothing okay well there's two
questions here and what one is sort of
how did it all get started question I'd
like to put that aside because I think
that's just going to get us into
arguments about you know a scientific
origin story and a non-scientific origin
story that I don't know we if we could
make much progress on that the other one
that I'm trying to get because I think
this maybe this is one of the reasons
why era Gina was saw thought to be a
heretic I mean because error Gina thinks
that eat that God's creation ultimately
doesn't leave God that God's creation is
ultimately an expression of an away and
and continuous with God's self knowledge
and that sounds to me also like what you
guys were saying earlier about the
manifestations of God are still God and
so I I'm not quite see what what you
want me to give up because I'm not sure
I'm not sure you you I'm not sure that
you gave it up earlier anyway they you I
mean up well I guess it's window jr. in
the way in which the ground of
possibility the ground of being will
constrain himself into making things
exist then the the question will be in
this manifestation is there how much
room I guess maybe is there left to
change to chance
how much relevance transition is there
guiding it towards something because I
could see if we just leave it there I
could see this leaving I could see this
going either way
where if we just take those two ideas
that well we know that there's a grow
that there's real possibility in the
world there is real emergence of things
and we don't know that they're there is
real constraints on those puzzle isn't
that the world exists between those two
if all we have is this it's sort of an
empirical question to see where will of
this meeting of emergence and emanation
lead where will this end - maybe this
meeting is conscious maybe it's not if
that's all yeah I think it could go both
ways yeah I think I mean III want to
acknowledge that because I think we're
all I mean we're all coming at this and
one of the users are like talking with
you guys well coming at this with
humility and we're all acknowledging we
don't have arguments that for clothes or
anything like that so yeah I I started I
see that - what you just said and I and
I I do like the idea that's why I
switched from similarity to conformity
that I I can put aside my worry about
similarity if there is a sense in which
right my mind can conform to reality not
in the content of mine but in like I say
in a very structural functional flow of
my mind that it is conforming to a de
structural functional flow of reality i
and that to me arm is a powerful thing I
think that's very close to fear with
this by the way this person yeah I think
so too I think that's I think that's
what theosis is as well I just I and I
don't want I think all of this is good
and what you just said I guess I even
though I've been responding to Marian
challenging her I I also respect her
concerns I there I keep asking this
question and I'm not trying to be
badgering
even after we view this I do I I have a
sense that you guys I sound like some
sort of alien species you guys have a
sense
that calls you beyond where if you'll
allow me to personalize this where I am
and and you know and and it like I say
there's sup and I use this one term very
broadly there's a phenom there's
something in your phenomenology and
there is happy to use that term I know
maybe I can tell you a story okay
recently you know I spent a few months
in France earlier this fall
and I had a chance to go to a special
Mass that was organized for that all the
students in Paris and they were like
three four thousand of us maybe and this
wasn't a fairly big church and old
church all made of stone beautiful
building so we were so many people we
couldn't even really sit down we could
either sit right on the floor or stand
up because we're so packed and you know
there were lots of also clergy there
there was like a few bishops several
priests the world also servers and so on
I know there was a great choir lots of
it so in a sense it was very involved
lots of people very intricately involved
and I remember there was a process
moment in in the mess where I I looked
up were singing some some enzyme
remember which ones and there's the very
sort of living continuty in what we sing
their songs we sing or like hundreds or
I don't maybe even more more than a
thousand years over and swimming Greek
some are in Latin so there's my teeth
historical depth to them right yeah that
people have been saying from the
beginnings of Christianity and we also
have some more modern songs but the
process moment where I remember was with
we were singing one of those and you
know in unison with lots of people
around me I had people I left around me
all combining our voices into one while
the the priests and the bishops were
also a portent we're all looking at them
towards the the altar and we was certain
sensing and I sort of looked up and I
saw this this old rock ceiling with a
thick layer of incense that had raised
up and
this felt really maybe otherworldly
would be putting it may be too too
strong cast it more Catholic I was as
much maybe in in the Middle Ages as I
was in - and 2019 I it really did feel
like when I was talking history earlier
about st. Maximus in his view of fuses
occurring within the body of Christ
where this new you this movement of
between the ground of intelligibility
and the college being which was so
broken by the fall and then the idea is
that when Christ became man he went all
the way down to to the bottom of things
yeah to the grown-ups for yeah yeah and
then when he you and then you raise
everything back up in a way that is
deeply continuous between the between
heaven earth between the ground of being
and the ground possibility because you
is both the Son of man having emerged
from from the earth and also the the Son
of God I think I get that yeah that's
very powerful yeah and then he raised us
by allowing us to enter into communion
with them so II it became very close to
twelve people made them his friends and
then when after after he died those
people those apostles founded churches
it's what they made loving connections
with people under them and this
established a hierarchy ultimately would
sit between heaven and earth and how
soon a a strong movement in history we
wish I can take part and by entering
into this I I get a strong sense of how
fuses where I I pursue it in something
that they just much larger than me that
is not just about me and that makes me
automatically want to love more everyone
around me sure and and I think that's
deeply important but I've had those
experiences and many people have had
those experiences in which again they
feel deep self transcendence they feel
the affordance of wisdom connection
communion they feel connected to
something much greater than so and many
of those people don't come out of that
with having sent having a sense of an
and countering a being or encountering
God or anything like that and they can
have I mean I I I had an experience very
similar when I went to Delphi and I
stood in front of the old fellows and
people have been there for millennia and
you have the part of that it goes down
into the ravine and for the earth and
part of it reaches up into the sky and
you get the sense of the continuity and
you know that Socrates had come you know
the people that come here and asked
about Socrates and all of that is there
and you get this yeah I've had I think
you know even a sense of being called by
on myself very deeply deeply connected
to the emanation and the emergence
that's why I wanted is why I talk about
this stuff because I've had these these
experiences um so again this may be your
ontology really is rich enough to know
and composite that the old phenomenology
and that's that's another person because
ultimately I think this is one point
especially when we talk about the
personalism of the ground maybe I
suspect maybe now that I may be even a
bit closer to you then to Mary
yeah yeah I think I was too rash in
saying that lots of Christians would be
happy with the deep continuity of
relevance realization up until the the
ground of being I think in the East
that's true most Christians would be
aptitude to leave it that well God is is
what person and beyond person even maybe
yeah yeah that what the father in
himself is only doing realms transition
with the son and not really maybe within
himself
I don't know maybe you could please play
with this well well I mean he is called
the logos and that would work that would
go very nicely with your what you've
just said maybe this is better left to
two particular theologians I mean please
Mary and I just want to acknowledge that
I do feel like we got a little closer in
an important way and I don't mean just
affectionately a book that's happening
is well I just met like I think you know
JP you often use the metaphor of bridge
building I think the chasm was less
chasm estat the bridge has to go across
if I could put it that way yeah
how's Mary okay I really like the stuff
that you said about the way that human
beings are prone to that the machinery
of relevance realization can be hijacked
they're prone to these perennial
problems and how the religious
traditions have honed the psycho
technologies to help them to deal with
that yes yes you said that very well you
you often interpret me very well so
here's my question here's a question
though that I have is that what I hear
you talk about the purpose of religion
as being - for for wisdom for as I'm
home for with medic and agape okay I
think what what I think about that is as
a Christian is that that's not the
primary purpose of our religion and I
cannot really speak that deeply about
other religions but I'm sure this is
true for Judaism you know Orthodox
Judaism and for Christianity is that for
us the primary purpose of the religion
is worship and the wisdom the whatever
the the wisdom effects on the human
person or that we would see them as a
byproduct of the worship so that you
know classically worship is seen as the
the virtue of justice has applied to the
relationship with the divine does that
mean treating the divine appropriately
is that what you mean appropriately in
the according according you know what
maybe they want to put in crude way
giving God what he deserves
sure you know and and then we carry that
further in the Christian tradition and
say we can't give God what he deserves
so we have to so Jesus comes in to give
himself to us so that we can give him
inside in a sacrificial way through the
Eucharist back
the father so that then we are giving
God what he really deserves and so but
that that the virtue of justice in the
soul or righteousness by the same word
is the word is the same translated
sometimes right sometimes justice is
that by developing that righteousness in
the soul through doing the worship that
is what then guys what then I would say
the the other wisdom the other wisdom
things follow from that the other
orderings of the soul followed from
follow from that so but the primary
purpose of our religion is not I'm
saying this because you're talking about
the religion that started religion and
wisdom and getting the wisdom and the
meaning and meaning but that that that's
I just wanted to say that that we don't
see that as the prime we don't see
getting wisdom as the primary purpose of
our religion so makes sense no I'm not
I'm not like I'm not trying to to say
that anything that you've said about it
is not correct had this extra element
that we that it's it's a it's a bit of a
truncated view of our religion to say
well the purpose is to be to gain wisdom
so sure
and I get that I want to ask you about
it I mean I mean I I could take some
biblical stuff like you know wisdom is
the principal thing from the book of
Proverbs so high up there is a priority
just that it's not it's the price it's
not the top priority yeah I want to be
fairly so let's do that
I mean so if you'll allow me a way of
talking about this because
I need a way of translating this into
you you know the phenomenology because I
don't want it just to be a circle of
doctrine I'm not saying you're saying
that so I'm what I'm doing I was trying
to translate it okay part of what you
might be saying is part of my
phenomenology is I feel called to
worship and that call being called to
worship I take to be the primary thing
of my religion I just say call but then
I I sense you know we talked about
creatureliness as part of the numinous
that has a creature in relation to the
Creator I am uh I am obligated to
worship that to not worship is to not be
fully a creature but that sounds to me
like the ultimate standard is again the
fullness of your being that but that you
can't come into a fullness of being
unless you're into the right
relationship with God so for example if
I
I mean this is tricky so you say you are
I'm trying to get above I was trying to
convey that with a sense of being called
in a sense that this is the right thing
for me to do right that it's appropriate
and right that I should treat the what's
ultimate I mean maybe fulfill X language
that I still don't I have to treat the
ultimate with ultimate concern and
anything less than ultimate concern is
not treating it as ultimate I'm trying
to use language that I can sort of make
work that's not specific to Christian
doctrines so it is it something like
that because because I get that I get so
you've heard me talk about the
difficulty with idolatry is we tend to
we treat something that's not ultimate
as if its ultimate and then that
radically disconnects
from reality and that that's - that's a
fundamental loss of meaning because
never idly meaning a semantic meaning
I mean connectedness to what's most real
and so it sounds to me like what you're
saying I'm sorry is that well what
worship means is I want I want the I
want I want to I want to realize the
most relevant connection to what's
ultimate and part of that means means
that I should always be treating it as
if it's ultimate is that is that right
well yes I should be treating I should
be treating God as as ultimate I should
be treating him in that way but other
religions do that I mean and right so
and other I mean so for example you know
Buddhism Buddhist said you know
everything that I do is for the ultimate
concern of Nirvana right if you like
everything is in the service of this and
it's not in the service of him right
it's that only in the relationship to
Nirvana well human beings achieve
enlightenment which is the Buddhist way
of trying to say the best possible life
they could achieve and and to use your
order of causation right the wisdom is
ultimately in the service of
enlightenment which is demister
ultimately in the service of realizing
Nirvana so that seems to be structurally
the case and that they at least deeply
structurally analogous in other
religions is that is that I'm not
familiar enough I'm sorry I don't mean
that's fine no no problem that I have
many have many am holes in my education
but I just want to say that if you ask
you know what is the what is
Christianity you know and see there are
some Christians who had said you ask
someone's Christianity about they'll say
well it's about getting saved but that's
a that's a rather truncated view of
Christianity really is about you know
that giving God what what is due him
and then like I said we know we can't
because of our fallenness give God what
is justly do him the praise and the
worship that is justly do him so he has
made that possible for him now that's
one part of it but that's like that's
the most important part and I would say
that shows in at least in the Catholic
and Orthodox churches end up the divine
liturgy or the mass the Eucharist is as
we Catholics say that the Orthodox would
agree the source and summit of our faith
it's that is a that is the sacrifice
provided to us to give back to God by
Christ by which all these by which all
the other things come listen the agape
the everything okay that's good so I
guess so the difference may be is that
in the way in which we can participate
in the groan of being its exhibits
closer to the body or closer to to to
matter in within Christianity where it's
not the way we confirm with the illness
with a cosmic relevance realization is
not just an effort on our part to let's
see do make a good form yeah it's not
just an effort on our part we also think
that God reaches down so that it became
the manifestations of the ground of D so
didn't don't just sort of do the bare
minimum may be obsessed anding the world
into existence so that things can can
emerge and so on but that and this is
this get pregnant to the point of
miracles but that and this would tie in
with the phenomenology we're in the
phenomenology of Christianity we may be
we we give a greater part of we
acknowledge more that may be the effort
that being does for us that the ground
of being does towards us you think
that's care is that fair to me or
furtive Mary Mary who are you are as
well to everyone
I mean I think I feel like you shift the
ground away from Mary ability I think
Mary was saying something like
independent of whatever it might have
done for us the ultimate is deserving of
being treated as ultimate and then but
that's how I put it and then I heard
Mary saying yeah John but something more
there there's I'm trying to put my is it
something like a sense of service I'm
trying to get what what's because not
all not only do their worship religions
right so the Buddhists don't worship
Nirvana but they think it's alternative
should be treated ultimately that's why
I'm saying that's why I'm saying that
it's a I'm saying that we have a
disjunction between okay I I hate
because when I hear you talking about
religion and like I say what you saying
about religion being these you know
containers for the set of psycho
technologies by which we gain wisdom
which i think is all is all true i
leaves out something in christianity i
believe also in judaism
although i don't know that much about
where Judaism Judaism sees itself either
now versus how the ancient Jews side
Chuck saw themselves it's also leave
living leaving something out of Islam in
the sense of submission to God because
that's what Islam means what I'm saying
is that in Christian it's leaving out in
Christianity the concept of worship as
that worship is the is what you know
what is the church for it's for worship
now you know beyond that of course
there's many other things there is the
wisdom there is the agape there is the
community there is there is them by
their fruits you shall know them to
write all that but but what is for is
worship that's why when Christ
establishes the church he does it at
that Eucharistic sacrifice with these
disciples and stuff so it's more thing
I guess maybe maybe this is part of it
then and so I want to tread very lightly
and I have to go soon guys but um so you
want to like I'm totally me I think it's
the Neoplatonic idea it's in Platonist
week right we we have to treat the
alternate ultimately and like I said
that's clearly in other religions and
then there's something you there's
something more you want to add here
about it's not just relating to what's
ultimate appropriately it's there's a
sense that God needs to be given things
is that is that what you're saying
because that's sort of futile to me that
because I don't think God needs anything
that would make that would that would
undermine everything we've been talking
about how everything is right so God
doesn't need that sort of the yeah the
son gives something to the father with
us that we can participate in what God
gives himself in distance is that sort
of what you're pointing at Mary well
remember when we were talking I know we
did this and also when I was talking to
Karen talking about the the you know a
lot of times we when we talk as
Christians we talk about Jesus loving us
you know that you know how much Christ
loved us that he sacrificed himself for
us and all but that the primary love of
Christ was the father that it's his love
for the father is the is what is what
was most in his you know his top
priority you know even over and above
his love for us that it was a obedience
to his father I would love for his
father so that it's the love between the
father and the son that is really what
creates everything because as the
creation is for the son it's to where
the Sun would have something to give to
the father so it's what creation is for
the father and the son is a is a way
that the father of the son express their
love for
on another and then draws into that draw
us into that love that they have for one
another and we've been speaking
Christian easier but we can translate it
into being in the ground of
intelligibility so I give thing
themselves to one another through us but
then but then we're back to what we were
talking about before and I think we
might have lost something in the circle
because I've already said that I think I
think part of what I was arguing for
when I was arguing for wisdom and
religion is to to fall deeply in love
with being for its own sake I mean
that's why that's why I invoke Spinoza
and then how would that so okay so we I
would say as a Christian so let's see if
we did the translation back and forth I
would say as a Christian that to fall to
fall in love with God is then to want to
give to God the praise that God deserves
but God knows that I cannot do that
and so God provides for me the means to
do that
okay that's the sacrifice of Christ
there's many other things accomplished
by that and you know that in Christian
theology but I'm just sticking with that
that well I I'm not trying to say that
you're making excuses claim so they take
that totally for granted okay so what
did you say just before Bali so I've my
question that would be okay so you have
fallen in love with being okay so the
ground being how do you express you know
and this is I'm not you know this is not
like an argument it's just like a you
know how do you express your love for
the ground of being how would you say
that works and you are
so if it depends what you mean I mean it
would be analogous to you come upon the
Grand Canyon and you realize there's
something above and beyond you and you
say ah you express our you express right
reverence and or like when I'm listening
to a I'm using I'm only using this as an
analogy because we're trying to talk
here so I'm using aesthetic analogy I'm
listening to perhaps you know the
seventh symphony by Beethoven and I feel
tremendous I it causes me to sense a
depths of thing a depth of things and I
and I love that depth I just feel the
love of that depth and I I appreciate in
both the senses of value and understand
and grow because appreciate means all of
those and I appreciate it very very
profoundly I get it so because to you
the ground of being is not personal then
then just merely having the personal
experience that you're having of
appreciating of feeling connected to it
that way that but but then we get back
to if you if you know the ground of
being as personal you can understand
then there would be a difference there
would be some phenomenologically
different responses to a person versus
it the non personal I get I get that I
get I get that I I totally acknowledge
and understand I think that there that
you want to say in worship I'm doing
something other than what you're doing
John but what I'm trying to get from the
other way but that's after you've
concluded that the ground is first of
all at which to me is to get the cart
before the horse I want to know what it
is and maybe this is where you have to
ultimately flee towards revelation or
something I want to know what it is in
the phenomenology that then
first it calls you to attribute the
person the person who had I don't want
sick personality because that's the
wrong word such that that worship they
make sense to you right we like my
question is my question is if what sorry
I just want to finish my point married
is just a sentence right my question
isn't what follows from you treating it
as a person my question was what lead
you to treat it as a person okay so I
would say crescents presence that you
get it so you get a sense of the of a
presence of a person yes hmm and then I
don't know and so that's what that and
not because in fairness to me I wasn't
around a lot of people who claimed that
and tried to get me to they brought me
up to try and experience that and feel
that so if it if that's what it comes
down to then I have nothing I have
nothing to say to you like and I don't
mean in the reticent I'm pulling away I
still want to be in relationship and
communion with you it says I don't and I
don't know what I don't know what to say
that yeah
so there is a there is the revelation
there is the you know the ontological
arguments about you know the creation
being a decision of a person there is
all that but then there is the sense of
presence which I think JP was kind of
hinting at him himself so there is a
there there is all you know there is all
of that that's why I say that when I
when I'm hearing you talk about what
religion is for I feel a little bit like
you're not it's not totally grasping
what we're experiencing within our
religious experience however that's not
to say that I would in any way impugn
the endeavor to bring as much wisdom
to people and is much a meaning to
people as possible but that but that I
think you know I Christians are still
going to be there we're still gonna be
around and we're stupid person there's a
person here we want you to get to know
we'll still be saying that to people and
so many of those people will get to know
that person they will have that
experience of presence and it will be
transformational for them in ways that
you would approve of I don't disagree
with that
I guess my I guess one thing to say back
is I was not trying to speak what about
what Christianity was because I think
it's fair for me to say that there are
things that are bona fide religions acts
your religions world religions in which
that sense of the presence of a person
is not felt or valorized within the
religion and so always trying to speak
as to what I think as I'm alternately in
the series I mean I'm trying to be a
scientist I'm trying to find what's what
are the universal principles of this
phenomena that doesn't mean that any
that that's not to dismiss everything
that we've been talking to or the point
the decision point that we became - I -
I do here I think there's a way in which
I mean Christians should keep doing what
you're doing
but I wanted to understand what I why
for me if I'm trying to talk about
religions and not Christianity that
can't be a defining feature right yeah I
yeah I I understand that but I just want
to do I just want to make the point that
that's kind of a do you think I've ever
disrespected Christianity no no no no
not at all although I do think maybe in
this conversation that I saw with you
today
a little bit dismissal dismissive of the
value of vowels but but that might be a
video with him I thought I thought well
you had two numbers numeral you know
[Laughter]
he's such a great he's such a great
character and I was listening to the
conversation I was outside I was
listening and when you were saying to
him how much he liked what he did you
were both laugh and I was he is becoming
a really important friend
for me yeah I think he's a valuable
partner in the project that that you're
that you're attempting and I'd like to
ask some more questions when we talk
again about how you see certain
practicalities of justified away how you
would deal with certain practicalities
in you're sure and other people have
been asking me that I've done a whole
bunch of interviews around to sort of
societal aspects and some of that will
be available and maybe get a chance to
listen to some of it I don't want to be
presumptuous and then we could circle
back around to it because I'm very happy
to talk with you two again I should go
guys so I'm sort of we're supposed to
stop at 8:45 I didn't want to stop
because I felt that like Mary and I were
framed you're leading to sort of a
really crucial and so I will acknowledge
I guess maybe formally and explicitly
hear that that is the piece of the
phenomenology that at least with
reference to Christianity or maybe the
Abrahamic religions is fair that is not
is not part of my experience and not for
lack of people trying to give it to me
either
so I
know what that means but yes now I see
what it is I think you have in your
experience and how you have it in your
experience and why you place the value
you do upon it so I think you have
answered my question in that way Mary
thank you thank you yeah you think
thanks to you both it's always a
pleasure
okay guys I was wondering if this time
in addition to being on your to your
channels both of you you could send me
it and I could also upload it to my
channel yeah yeah I can send it to the
both of you
probably sometime tomorrow morning
that'd be fantastic I'm at a conference
speaking at a conference tomorrow so
that that'll be fun for me so we will
I'm sure we will all talk again I
enjoyed this thoroughly and thank you
very much I appreciate everybody's you
know affection and respect and charity
and entering into good-faith discussion
I deeply appreciate it and thankful for
it yes and thank you both for your work
as well thank you good night
bye guys